Guide to the William C. Kingsley family collection ARC.047
Brooklyn Historical Society
William C. Kingsley family collection
1867-1964
Brooklyn Historical Society
Kingsley family
Kingsley, William C.
Thornton, Mary Beth
Marcinkowski, Janet
ARC.047
0.75 Linear Feet in two document boxes.
William C. Kingsley (1833-1885) had a prominent role in the building of the Brooklyn Bridge. This collection pertains to Kingsley and his family as well as the Brooklyn Bridge and includes scrapbooks, publications, correspondence, and a photograph.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of the collection was the gift of Janet Marcinkowski, 1988. The 1867 letter and its related clipping were the gift of Mary Beth Thornton, 2023.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two boxes by type: the bound volumes are housed in Box 2 and arranged by size and binding, and the loose items are housed in Box 1 and arranged chronologically.
Biographical note
William C. Kingsley (1833-1885) was a businessman, politican, and engineer who is most well-known for his prominent role in the building of the Brooklyn Bridge. He was born in Fort Covington, N.Y., and at the age of 18 moved to Westmoreland County, PA, to work as a clerk for his brother, a railroad contractor. Later he worked as a clerk for Colonel Snodgrass, a canal contractor, in Wyoming County, PA. When the Superintendent of the project left his post prematurely, Kingsley became Superintendent of the building of the canal, seeing the project through successfully. He then worked as a railroad civil engineer, building a tunnel on the Pennsylvania Central Railroad between the towns of Altoona and Johnstown. As his reputation as a highly competent engineer grew, Kingsley took on greater responsibilities, overseeing the construction of railroads in Illinois, Wisconsin, and other states further west. Kingsley finally settled in Brooklyn, N.Y. in 1861, and after overseeing the successful completion of the Brooklyn City Waterworks, he went into partnership with Abner C. Keeney, primary owner of the Brooklyn Daily Eagle newspaper. The firm of Kingsley & Keeney would go on to build miles of sewerage in Brooklyn and New York, as well as the stone walls surrounding Central Park and Brooklyn's Washington Park.
Kingsley's connection with the Brooklyn Bridge began in 1866, when he played an instrumental role in generating interest among wealthy members of the private sector in the prospect of a bridge connecting the two cities of Brooklyn and New York. When the building of the bridge commenced with the incorporation of the New York Bridge Company in 1867, Kingsley & Keeney were the owners of the largest share of private stock in the company, and Kingsley was made a member of the Board of Trustees. He later became Vice President of the company in 1875, and President in 1882, overseeing the completion and opening of the bridge in 1883. Kingsley resigned from his presidency of the company in December of 1884.
Aside from his work as an engineer and contractor, Kingsley was also actively involved in much of the political and business life of Brooklyn. He was a member of the Democratic National Committee, a frequent delegate to the Democratic National Convention, and a member of the State Capitol Commission. Along with his partner Abner C. Keeney, Kingsley was the primary owner of the Brooklyn Daily Eagle, and upon Keeney's death in the summer of 1884, Kingsley became the principal owner of the paper. Kingsley died, reportedly of pneumonia, at his home in Brooklyn in February of 1885, after suffering from ill health for nearly a year. At the time of his death he was one of the wealthiest citizens in Brooklyn.
Kingsley was married to Kate Cook Kingsley, and the couple had three children. One son, Harry Smith Kingsley (1863-1900), was a decorated military officer and the Treasurer of the Brooklyn Daily Eagle before dying at the age of 37 in Florence, Italy. Another son, James Cooke Kingsley, was also an engineer, and a daughter, Anna Kingsley Thayer, was the wife of Boston banker Albert Thayer.
Sources:
"Death List of a Day." The New York Times, October 2, 1900. Accessed July 16, 2010. http://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive-free/pdf?res=9A04E3D81039E733A25751C0A9669D946197D6CF
"Death of W.C. Kingsley." The New York Times, February 21, 1885. Accessed July 16, 2010. http://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive-free/pdf?res=9A04E3D81039E733A25751C0A9669D946197D6CF
Related Materials
William C. Kingsley and John B. Woodward engrossed resolutions (1989.005)
Brooklyn Bridge construction records (1977.259)
Brooklyn Bridge photographs (V1986.249)
Brooklyn Bridge golden anniversary dinner seating list (1992.002)
Scope and Contents
The William C. Kingsley familiy collection spans the period circa 1870 to 1950 and pertains to William C. Kingsley and his family, as well as the Brooklyn Bridge. Materials include a letter from Kingsley to his sister and a clipping with a transcription of the letter; a letter of credit to Kingsley's daughter Anna, issued by Drexel, Morgan & Co. of London, England; two copies of a memorial volume published in tribute to Kingsley upon his death in February 1885; two letters of condolence to Kingsley's wife Kate Cook Kingsley; five copies of a memorial volume published in tribute to Kingsley's son, Harry Smith Kingsley, upon his death in 1900; a publication commemorating the 50th anniversary of the Brooklyn Bridge in 1933, as well as a program for the 50th anniversary ceremony; and a scrapbook containing newspaper clippings on members of the Kingsley-Swan family, as well as the business and social affairs in which they were involved, spanning at least four generations. A small number of clippings in the scrapbook pertain to the Brooklyn Bridge. The collection also includes a mounted print of the Brooklyn Bridge taken from the Brooklyn side of the East River, and a copy negative of the image, as well as a scrapbook of correspondence and ephemera related to the Brooklyn Bridge's opening, compiled by Kingsley.
Letters of credit; Brooklyn Bridge (New York, N.Y.); Biographies; Engineers -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Programs (documents); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; Volumes (documents by form); Families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Clippings (information artifacts); Scrapbooks; Photographs; Publications; Correspondence; Brooklyn Bridge (New York, N.Y.) -- Anniversaries, etc.; Thayer, Anna Kingsley; Kingsley, Kate Cook; Kingsley, William C.; New York Bridge Company; Kingsley, Harry Smith; Kingsley family; Thornton, Mary Beth; Marcinkowski, Janet
- William C. Kingsley letter to sister and related clipping, 1867, 1964; 2024.024 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Mary Beth Thornton, 2023.
- William C. Kingsley Brooklyn Bridge scrapbook, 1883; 1977.330 (Box 2)
- Loose items from William C. Kingsley scrapbook, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Anna S. Kingsley letter of credit, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Condolence letters to Kate C. Kingsley, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- William C. Kingsley memorial volume (2 copies), 1885 (Box 2)
- Brooklyn Bridge photograph, circa late 19th century-early 20th century; V1987.053 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Scope and Contents
  Original albumen print mounted on board, modern copy print, and copy negative.
- Harry Smith Kingsley memorial volume (5 copies), 1900 (Box 2)
- Swan family scrapbook, circa 1908-1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Parish Notes newsletter, 1918 September (Box 1, Folder 7)
  From the Church of the Redeemer, 4th Avenue and Pacific Street, Brooklyn. Includes a note memorializing Kingsley Swan.
- Brooklyn Bridge 50th anniversary booklets, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)